Guide to the John Zuccotti Papers 1956-2015 MS 3018
New-York Historical Society
- Series V. Speeches and Other Presentations, 1967-2015; 3.25 Linear feet
  - Writings (2 folders), 1977-1982, 2009 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5-6)
    Includes "Housing Development: Joint Ventures Between Community Non Profit Organizations and Private Developers," co-written with Andrew S. Berkman and published under a different title in the National Law Journal of 7 May 1979; Zuccotti's paper, "A Vision of America's Urban Future," prepared for Columbia's General Education Seminar "The City and the University," with transcript of discussion (1979); "How the Crisis Opened the Door for Management" for the Economic Development Council of New York City (1977); "Impact of New Midtown Zoning on Development" for Vol. 1, No. 1 of the developers' newsletter Developments; untitled articles for ABO Newsletter and Realty (circa 1980); and a "Be Our Guest" column for the Daily News headlined as "Green shoots at Ground Zero" (2009).
  - Audiotape. "The Lynn & Sy Syms Show" Guest: John Zuccotti, 1997 April 30 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
  - Speech Working Material, 1968-1970s? (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
    Includes documents found together in a notebook. In addition to the notebook with notes on urban planning matters, there is an undated essay "The Crisis of Confidence"; an undated essay "Science and the City: Rhetoric and Reality" co-written with James D. Carroll; a program for the 1968 National Housing Center Council's Senior Executives Conference, with Zuccotti's extensive notations; a confirmation of Zuccotti's 1972 appearance on a panel at Citizens Housing & Planning Council; and two loose sheets of notes.
  - Speech Working File (2 folders), 1967-1980s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9-10)
    The overall theme of these folders seems to be zoning. The folders include a paper "Impact of New Midtown Zoning on Development," written by Zuccotti while a partner at Tufo & Zuccotti in the early 1980s. Other documents include speeches made by Zuccotti in the mid-1970s while City Planning Commission Chairman; 1967-1968 speeches by HUD officials; a document "A Federal Housing Strategy/A National Urban Policy" sent to Zuccotti from HUD in 1977; a transcript of Zuccotti's comments at an EDC Board of Directors meeting on 14 June 1977; and various notes and outlines for remarks.
  - Speech Working File. Fiscal Crisis, circa 1982-1985 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 11)
    These documents, dating from the mid-1980s, appear to relate to a speech or article concerning reflections on the fiscal crisis of the mid-1970s. Includes notes "Steps taken before MAC came into existence (June 1975)"; a Comptroller's report "Comparative Analysis of New York City's Financial and Economic Indicators for Second Quarter Fiscal Year 1982"; photocopies of 1985 press clippings; a copy of Jim Sleeper's 1985 article "Ed Koch & the Spirit of the Times," inscribed by Sleeper; a partial draft of an article for the New York Times Magazine; Volume 18, No 3 (1985) of City Almanac,, with articles on the crisis; and Zuccotti's handwritten draft outline/notes "The Fiscal Crisis, 1975-1978."
  - Speech Working Material (Folder 1 of 4), circa 1967-1980s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12)
    Includes loose documents found together in the original collection, mostly handwritten notes for various unidentified remarks and reference material.
  - Speech Working Material (Folder 2 of 4), circa 1967-1980s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 13)
    Includes notes for remarks and reference material, including a paper "Towards an Effective National Housing Policy"; a speech by U.S. Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan "Urban Policy Revisited" (1977); a suggested outline from HUD for a paper "Housing in an Urban Strategy" (1977); remarks by HUD Undersecretary Robert Wood (1967); Draft #4 of a paper "A Federal Housing Strategy/A National Urban Policy" (1977); and Zuccotti's notes for his paper "Impact of New Midtown Zoning on Development."
  - Speech Working Material (Folder 3 of 4), 1983-1985 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 14)
    Includes two 1983 reports from Program Planners, Inc.: "New York City: Fiscal Issues and the Financial Plan, FY1984," and "Crisis or Stability: New York City's Fiscal Condition." Also includes more handwritten and other notes from Zuccotti originally found within the pages of the Program Planners reports.
  - Speech Working Material (Folder 4 of 4), 1985 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15)
    Includes documents related to a forum concerning the Board of Estimate held by the Committee on Municipal Affairs of the Association of the Bar of the City of New York, at which Zuccotti was a panelist for the topic "Land Use and Zoning." Includes program, participant list, and various papers on the forum's subject.
  - Speech Working File (3 folders), circa 1977-1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 16-18)
    Includes reference material and documents related to various programs at which Zuccotti spoke. Includes a reprint of the article "Zoning Obscenity: Or, The Moral Politics of Porn" by Norman Marcus (1978); writings by Zuccotti for "Realty" and "ABO Newsletter"; Zuccotti's notes for remarks for a Bar Association panel on the landmarks law; Manhattan Borough President Andrew J. Stein's paper "Beyond New York's Renaissance" and related New York Times opinion pieces (1982); a draft New York Times Magazine article (presumably by Zuccotti); a membership directory and by-laws for the Young Men's Real Estate Association of New York (1981-82); testimony by Queens Borough President Donald R. Manes before the Human Resources Administration and its Advisory Board (1982); an address by U.S. Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan "World Trade and World Peace" (1982); Daniel Rose's commencement address for MIT's Center for Real Estate Development (1986); Robert C. Weaver's article "The First Twenty Years of HUD" (1985); Volume 18, No. 4 of City Almanac which focuses on "The Redevelopment of 42nd Street"; a transmittal to Zuccotti from Mayor Edward I. Koch with a response and statistics disputing conclusions in Raymond Horton and Charles Brecher's "Setting Municipal Priorities: 1986" (or "SMP", a source found often in Zuccotti's speech files); notes for Zuccotti's remarks at Manhattan Institute for Policy Research's conference "New York Unbound: The City and the Politics of the Future" (1988);, and remarks by Mayor Koch at a City Planning Commission conference (1988).
  - Speech Material, 1970s-1986 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 19A)
    Includes Zuccotti's remarks on "neighborhoods" to an audience that included Mayor Beame and Rabbi Sherer; program and rough outline for remarks at a seminar held by the Real Estate Board of New York (1982); and the Citizens Budget Commission report "The City of New York's 1987 Executive Budget: Analysis & Recommendations" (June 1986).
  - Speech Material, 1992 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 19B)
    Includes a copy of the September 1992 volume of the American Planning Association's magazine Planning with brief notes from Zuccotti inside.
  - Speech File. New York City Partnership, 2000, 2004 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 20)
    Includes a draft article on legislative leadership in New York State (2000), documents regarding Zuccotti's membership in the New York City Partnership (2000), and the program for the 31st annual awards luncheon of the New York Housing Conference and National Housing Conference at which Zuccotti received the Lifetime Achievement Award (2004).
  - Speech Material, 2004-2009 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 21)
    Includes, among other documents, Zuccotti's article "Against All Odds--Why New York Works" (2003); an invitation card for the retirement party of Sonny Hall, International President of the Transport Workers Union of America, AFL-CIO (2004); a New York City Independent Budget Office Fiscal Brief "Comparing State and Local Taxes in Large Cities" (2007); Daniel Rose's remarks "New York--Today and Tomorrow" at the Urban Land Institute (2009); and background statistics and draft speech related to economic troubles (2008).
  - Speech Material (3 folders), 2003, 2010-2012 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 22-24)
    Includes Zuccotti's keynote address "Against All Odds--Why New York Works" before the Toronto Real Estate Forum and a shortened version for publication in Real Estate Weekly" (2003), and scattered notes and other documents related to Zuccotti's remarks at the Yale Alumni Real Estate Asociation Conference (2012). Includes some reference material including slides from a PowerPoint presentation giving an overview of Brookfield Asset Management, Inc. (2012) and a marketing booklet for Brookfield Office Properties.
  - Speech Material, 2013 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 25)
    Includes background material for a discussion on strategic leadership at a Brookfield management meeting, notes for Zuccotti for an interview at a Brookfield Executive Committee meeting, and preparation notes for Zuccotti's appearance on a panel "The New York City Office Market: Forty Years at Forty Thousand Feet."
  - Speech File. Lunch at Norwegian Consul General, 2013 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 26)
  - Yale Seminar (2 folders), 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-2)
    Includes student papers, course outline, and other material related to Zuccotti's seminar taught at Yale Law School "Large-Scale Real Estate Transactions." Also includes general administrative documents such as faculty directories, schedules and bulletin of classes.
  - Columbia Seminar (2 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3-4)
    Includes the syllabus, readings and other material concerning the Fall 1990 course "Land Use: Regulation and Development" co-taught by Zuccotti and Victor Marrero.
  - Columbia Seminar, 1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Columbia Seminar (2 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - Columbia Seminar (4 folders), 1996 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-4)
  - Columbia Miscellaneous, 1987-1990s (Offsite-box 10, Folder 5)
    Includes a faculty handbook (1987), President's Report (1993-1994) and miscellaneous notes and class readings.
  - Seminar Materials (4 folders), undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6-9)
    Includes topical outlines and readings for historic preservation, zoning, and other land use topics.
- Series VI. General Subjects, 1966-2013; 4.71 Linear feet
  The series includes a broad range of subject matter related to John Zuccotti and his public service, professional career, and other interests. Much of the series includes publications or other forms of reports on the topics of economic development, housing, zoning, planning, and transportation. These touch both general strategies or proposals for action in New York City and more specific initiatives and locales, notably in lower Manhattan.
  Several files include material closely related to Zuccotti. These include documents concerning Material Systems Corporation, for which Zuccotti served as a Director, and its business of manufacturing low-cost factory-produced housing for HUD (early 1970s); a chronology of New York's fiscal crisis of the mid-1970s; labor-management issues from the period during which Zuccotti served as an Impartial Arbitrator (1980s); some documents from the financial struggles of Olympia & York (early 1990s); and emails and other documents concerning Brookfield's response to the Occupy Wall Street protest in Zuccotti Park (2011). The container list includes detailed reference to the specific subjects, reports, and other material in this highly varied series.
  The series is organized by subject matter in roughly chronological order.
  - The Lower Manhattan Plan. New York City Capital Project ES-1. Oversize, 1966 June 1 (Offsite-box 16)
    Report prepared for the New York City Planning Commission by architects and planners Wallace, McHarg, Roberts, and Todd; architects and planners Whittlesey, Conklin and Rossant; and transportation & planning consultants Alan M. Voorhees & Associates.
  - Draft Report: "Federal Programs and the Development of Lysander: A Report Submitted to the Syracuse University Research Corporation Policy Institute", 1969 April 25 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10)
    Includes a draft co-authored by Zuccotti and James D. Carroll, apparently in connection with work for the National Corporation for Housing Partnership.
  - Memorandum re: Tufo & Zuccotti New York Office Design Administration, 1969 December 26 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11)
  - Lincoln Square: Community Action Planning Program, 1970? (Offsite-box 10, Folder 12)
    Includes the report issued by Lincoln Square Community Council and the New York City Department of City Planning.
  - Land Banking: Public Policy Alternatives and Dilemmas, 1970 December 8 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
    Includes draft report/working paper 112-28 by Sylvan Kamm, issued by The Urban Institute.
  - U.S. House of Representatives Panels on Housing (2 folders), 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 14-15)
    Includes preliminary summaries of three study panels held in late 1970 by the Subcommittee on Housing of the House Committee on Banking and Currency; the full remarks, "The Goals of Housing Subsidy Programs," by one of the panelists, Morton L. Isler; the final report and recommendations issued by the committee in June 1971 under the title "Housing and the Urban Environment," and two copies of Part II of the published versions of the panels' papers (Part I not in the collection).
  - Material Systems Corporation (3 folders), 1970-1973 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 16-18)
    Material Systems Corporation (MSC) developed and manufactured low cost factory produced homes, garden apartments and townhouses. A primary part of its business was in connection with HUD's experimental housing program, Operation Breakthrough. Zuccotti was on the company's Board of Directors. The documents include a draft "Introduction" to the company with product descriptions, organizational information, financial data, etc. (1972); a preliminary prospectus for a public stock offering (1972); a proposal for the company to develop low cost housing in Mexico, with related assessments about foreign expansion; and the Board minutes of 21 March 1973 concerning the company's refinancing.
  - Planning for Jobs. Oversize, 1971 March (Offsite-box 16)
    Includes the New York City Planning Commission's supplement to "Plan for New York City."
  - Joint Venture with Walker & Dunlop, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 19)
    Includes documents related to the possibility of the firms Tufo, Johnson and Zuccotti and Walker & Dunlop forming a development company specializing in FHA programs. In addition to cost benefit and other analyses of the organization, there are some documents related to then active projects (Skytower Apartments in Washington, DC; Mall View Apartments in Frederick and Leafy House Apartments in Silver Spring, Maryland; Winchester Gardens in Winchester, Virginia; and others not specified by name).
  - City Planning Commission, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 20)
    Includes a few documents related to Zuccotti's term on the Commission: a letter supporting Zuccotti's vote in favor of low rent housing in Battery Park City; Report of Investigation Concerning Forest Hills Low-Income Housing Project by Mario Cuomo; reprint of Roger Starr's "The Lesson of Forest Hills"; the report of Citizens Housing & Planning Council's Committee on City-Aided Mitchell-Lama Housing; pages 2-49 of a task force report concerning housing; and a letter from Two Trees describing their proposal to co-op Park Terrace Gardens (1973).
  - "The Group", 1973 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 21)
    Includes documents related to "The Group" comprised of various individuals, including Zuccotti and S.F. Boden of the Association for Middle Income Housing, that formed to consider solutions to housing problems in New York City.
  - Fiscal Crisis Chronology (4 folders), 1974-1981 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-4)
    Includes a "Chronology of Important Disclosures Concerning City of N.Y.'s Fiscal Conditions," 1974-75, with copies of press releases and other related documents; chronologies covering 1974-1981 concerning various aspects of the crisis, prepared by Program Planners, Inc.; and various clippings.
  - "Reports of the Department of City Planning and Letters of Response", 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
    Includes the content of a binder: covers (only) of various city reports and copies of letters from individuals or organizations expressing appreciation of the report.
  - Economic Development Corporation (4 folders), 1973-1977 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6-9)
    Includes a position description for Deputy Mayor for Economic Development; copies of memos from Deputy Mayor Osborn Elliott to Mayor Beame concerning economic recovery; a draft prospectus and a proposal for an Economic Development Corporation, and various recovery concepts; the report Economic Recovery: New York City's Program for 1977-1981; an economic recovery progress report as of October 1977; a draft analysis of the PBA's annuity deferral; a copy of the Neighborhood Strategy Areas: A Guidebook for Local Government; and some of Zuccotti's speeches and testimony from 1973-1975.
  - Economic Recovery Related Memos, 1977 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 10)
    Includes a fact sheet prepared for Zuccotti on New York's tax abatement and building incentive programs; a memo prepared for Mayor Beame on the President's National Energy Plan; and memos on the city's economic development legislative package.
  - Planning Reports, 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 11)
    Includes three reports: Cooperative Community Planning (June 1977) and A New Zoning for New York City (July 1977), both issued by the City Planning Commission, and A New Partnership to Conserve America's Communities: A Status Report on the President's Urban Policy" (June 1978), issued by the White House.
  - Eve's Rights: A Guide to the Rights of Women in New York State, 1977 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 12)
    Booklet prepared by Eve Cary for the New York Civil Liberties Union
  - South Bronx Redevelopment, 1978, 1980 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 13)
    Includes an unattributed preliminary draft of "Proposal for the South Bronx" (11 April 1978) and a memo "analyzing comparative performance capacities of alternative implementation systems proposed for the South Bronx" issued by the South Bronx Development Office (August 1980).
  - West Side Highway Project: Final Environmental Impact Statement and Section 6 of the Final Environmental Impact Statement: Comments and Responses on the Draft Environmental Impact Statement (2 folders), circa 1978 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 14-15)
  - "125th Street Shopping Mall Complex: Application for Block Grant Funding", 1977, 1979 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 16)
    Includes portions of Volume II submitted by the Harlem Urban Development Corporation; these include the report "Commercial Development Impact on 125th Street, Harlem, New York" (1977) prepared by Jerome Michael & Associates; site appraisals; and "Harlem Two Year Development Plan: Summary" (1977).
  - Economic Development Reports (2 folders), 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 17-18)
    Includes Agenda for Economic Development issued by Mayor Beame's Policy Committee (1975); the proceedings of the institute sponsored by the New York City Council on Economic Education (25 April 1979), inscribed by participant Albert Alexander to Robert F. Wagner, Jr.; Regional and Economic Development Strategies for the 1980s (May 1979), issued by the Port Authority of NY & NJ's Committee on the Future; and Report on Economic Conditions in New York City"] (15 September 1979).
  - Economic Development Advisory Council (2 folders), 1976-1980 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 19-20)
    Includes documents related to Zuccotti's participation on Governor Hugh Carey's Advisory Committee (1980): copy of the final report submitted to Carey over Felix Rohatyn's signature on behalf of the Committee, the Regional Plan Association's favorable response and a related 1980 paper "Manhattan's Future" from the RPA, minutes of the Committee's meeting of 9 April 1980 and Rohatyn's summary and action points from the meeting, and three reports (1976) from the Business/Labor Working Group headed by David Rockefeller of Chase Manhattan Bank and Harry Van Arsdale of the Central Labor Council, AFL-CIO.
  - "Midtown Development Project" Report, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 21)
    Includes the draft report (June 1980) issued by the Department of City Planning, and the New York Chapter of the American Institute of Architects' comments on it (10 March 1981).
  - The Future of the World Trade Center, 1981 April (Offsite-box 11, Folder 22)
    Includes the report to Governor Hugh L. Carey of the World Trade Task Force, formed by Carey and chaired by Zuccotti.
  - New York City Procedural Guides, 1982-1983, 1990 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 23)
    Includes three booklets: New York City Tax Guide (1982), issued by the Department of Finance; Rules of Procedure (1983), issued by the Board of Standards and Appeals; and Zoning Handbook: A Guide to New York City's Zoning Resolution (1990).
  - City Planning for Buildings, 1983-1985? (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
    Includes two publications: Lofts: Balancing the Equities (June 1983), issued by the City Planning Commission, and The Report of the Mayor's [Koch] Blue Ribbon Panel on Building Plan Examination and Review (1985?).
  - Theater District Program, 1983 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2)
    Includes two copies of the proposed project description prepared for the Shubert, Nederlander and Jujamcyn Organizations by Cooper, Eckstut Associates.
  - Diaries of Mario M. Cuomo: The Campaign for Governor, 1984 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3)
    Includes the booklet published by Random House as a "special limited edition of excerpts for the friends of Governor Cuomo and Random House."
  - Speeches by Robert Wood, 1984-1986, 1990, 1994 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 4)
    Includes Wood's "Black Leadership Styles: What's Best for the Eighties?" (1984), "The Great Society in 1984: Relic or Reality?" (1984), "A Profession [Human Services] in Double Jeopardy" (1985), "Lifting the Siege" (1985), "Mayor Richard Lee [of New Haven, Conn.]: A National Vantage" (1986), "Present Before the Creation [of the Great Society and HUD]: Lessons from the Paleozoic Age of Urban Affairs" (1990), an informal recollection by Wood on "How History Should Remember President Johnson" (1994), and Philip Brownstein's recollections of how HUD's Austin Oaks housing project came to be (1994). Zuccotti is mentioned in the last item, which was forwarded to him by Wood for comment.
  - Labor/Management Relations (Folder 1 of 6), 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 5)
    Includes the Reports to the Legislature for NYS-OER/CSEA's Joint Labor-Management Committee on Work Environment and Productivity, NYS-OER/Council 82 AFSCME's Joint Labor-Management Committee on Quality of Work Life, and NYS-OER/PDQ's Joint Labor-Management Committee on Professional Development and Quality of Working Life (1982); the New York State Committee on the Work Environment and Productivity Progress Report for 1979-1982; program and relalted documents for the First Annual Conference on New York City Public Transit (12 December 1982); and clippings and other documents related to labor relations and programs.
  - Labor/Management Relations (Folder 2 of 6), 1982, 1984 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 6)
    Includes the agreement between the New York City Transit Authority and Subway-Surface Supervisors Association (August 1982) and "An Outline of Procedure Under Arbitration Law in New York" (1984).
  - Labor/Management Relations (Folder 3 of 6), 1983, 1985 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 7)
    Includes Zuccotti's remarks and documents related to the Subway-Surface Supervisors Association Stewards Seminar of 1983 and 1985.
  - Labor/Management Relations (Folder 4 of 6), 1989-1989 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 8)